if we would have the occasion to visit
Western Europe
at this time in history
and go on the tours that feature visits
to the great Cathedrals and the churches
of Western Europe we
soon discover that many of them
have become museums
and what some cynics refer to as the
mausoleums for the death of God and
of Christianity
the last figure I saw was that a roughly
two percent of people in Western Europe
are regular in attending church
and that the culture in the main has
been secularized and historians look
back to the 18th century and see in the
18th century some pivotal events that
took place then that have led to the
demise of the church in the life of
people in the western world
we've seen already that the 18th century
can be called the age of empiricism
because of what was going on in Great
Britain with respect to the questions of
epistemology that were dealt with with
people like Locke and Barkley and Hume
but also the 18th century is famous for
a movement that is called the
enlightenment
and even though the 17th century was
called The Age of Reason from an
epistemological perspective the 18th
century is also sometimes referred to as
the Age of Reason not because of the
distinction between rational and
empirical Trends in philosophical
inquiry but now because of the
enthronement of reason with a capital R
over against the idea of biblical
Revelation the 14th and 15th centuries
brought the Renaissance to Europe and
during that period as we have seen there
was an attempt to focus people's
attention on this world and to focus
philosophical energy on understanding
man for mankind as it were
one of the most important voices as
we've already seen for the the
Renaissance thinkers was that of Erasmus
who was supposedly a Christian humanist
but we saw the whole movement of
humanism developing a following not only
inside the church but also as an
alternative to the Christian Community
but those forces of the Renaissance were
Then followed immediately by the 16th
century Reformation which saw a strong
current of Revival of biblical
Christianity
and in the 16th century we noticed that
one of the chief debates at the time was
between Martin Luther
and Erasmus and the subject that they
debated was the question of man's Fallen
nature the doctrine of original sin
particularly as it influences our
understanding of human freedom
now in that debate in the 16th century
historians were usually
grant that Erasmus lost that struggle
and Luther and the reformers were
triumphant in restoring a strong
augustinian theology to the Protestant
world
and it's also true that in the 17th
century Luther and the reformers
maintained their victory over the
humanness of the earlier period but by
the time we reached the 18th century in
Europe
we can say that where Erasmus lost the
battle in the 16th century in the 17th
century to Luther
the 18th century is the age of the
Triumph of humanism and of the forces of
Erasmus over the Reformation because at
the heart of Luther's theology of
Calvin's theology both of whom were so
heavily dependent on Augustine was the
view that man as the Bible suggests is
corrupt in the core of his being and has
because of a historical fall
is now caught up in this uh
bondage of the human will to evil
impulses
the 18th century saw a strong reaction
against the whole notion of the Fall
against original sin against augustinian
theology against Luther and Calvin and
the rest with this movement called the
enlightenment
now in Germany the enlightenment was
called the auf claron which is simply
the German word for enlightenment and
the enlightenment was a strong force
basically in three countries Germany
France and England
and the thinking that came out of the
18th century Enlightenment had a
tremendous formative influence on the
new world as it was emerging here in the
United States and
also for the future of Western Europe
and when we go back to the 18th century
and look at the enlightenment
we see that the period did not present
to us a monolithic movement and
sometimes people who look at the 18th
century and speak of the Enlightenment
sometimes caricature of the
Enlightenment as if it were a unified
systemic movement where all the
philosophers believed basically the same
thing namely that it was a monolithic
experience but that's not the case at
all there were a host of thinkers
engaged in this movement called The
Enlightenment and they run the gamut on
on the philosophical spectrum and
Theological Spectrum from
the still highly religious to those that
were absolutely cynical and skeptical
and hostile towards any kind of religion
but as far as epistemology was concerned
the Enlightenment thinkers shared for
the most part a common approach to
knowledge
which was called the analytical method
and this method was a method that
had been born in the laboratory of
Natural Science because of the
tremendous advances in astronomy in
physics in mathematics and in the other
Sciences with the discovery of the
so-called scientific method
the thinkers of this time
were now applying this method of
learning not only to Natural Sciences
like biology and chemistry and physics
but also they began to apply this
methodology to what we would call the
social sciences and I'll give a couple
of examples of that as we proceed but
again the startling results of the
copernican Revolution the alleleos
experiments and so on and now
specifically with the impact of the
whole new scientific Paradigm brought
about chiefly through the work of Isaac
Newton Newtonian physics was indeed
revolutionary
now Newton himself
had a very strong religious bent in fact
he saw his work as a scientist in his
own terms and his own words as being
engaged in thinking God's thoughts after
him
but not everyone in this new emerging
science had the same appreciation for
religion that Newton did
and so this analytical method can be
simply defined as this that the task of
philosophy and the task of science is to
seek the logic of the facts
this is basically empirical in its uh
initial stages that is as the scientist
gathers his data empirically
he gets the individual pieces of
information
now thus the scientist is told to apply
the rational skills of deduction to the
inductive approach of collecting data
experimenting with the data and so on
and to see if the data yields an
observable pattern
or a coherent system that's what is
meant by looking for the logic of the
facts now the idea here is is that you
don't begin with some kind of
philosophical system and then use that
as a grid to cover the facts and try to
squeeze the facts into your preconceived
system
but rather the system is to emerge from
a study of the facts I run into this
problem all the time in teaching
Systematic Theology that's one of the
courses that I teach in the Seminary and
that's basically my field Systematic
Theology and I noticed with each passing
year a greater antipathy
and distrust towards the very concept of
systematic theology
students today have this kind of allergy
against any kind of system
we're an anti-system
society and so often the accusation is
that the systematic Theologian has a
theological framework and then he comes
to the Bible and he tries to interpret
every piece of information in the Bible
into that framework or that theological
system which would then of course
involve us in a serious Distortion of
what is in the Bible
and so you have this clash between
so-called Systematic Theology and
biblical theology on the other hand
where the biblical theologians pay
attention to the details of the various
portions of scripture and astew putting
them together in any kind of system well
what Systematic Theology has meant
historically is not to come with a
preconceived system to the Bible but
it's simply to look for the logic of the
facts that is to see the holistic
comprehensive
coherent
relationship of all of the individual
parts of the Bible that is the
assumption is is that the Bible is Unity
the Bible is coherent it comes
ultimately from God and so we could
should be able to find an inner logic in
it but in any case that's just an
illustration or example of this approach
to knowledge which I think is basically
a sound approach
I have no complaint to make essentially
against the analytical method or what we
would call the scientific method today
as long as it is used properly
but one of the fascinating developments
in the enlightenment was I said that
this new excitement and confidence in
the developments in progress in physics
and biology and so on
this PR this principle of the analytical
method was then transferred in an
attempt to understand the social
sciences
for example
uh Montesquieu
as an Enlightenment thinker wrote his
famous book called The Spirit of the
laws where he examined
all of the different civilizations
that he was aware of historically
throughout the history of the West and
he looked for patterns
and just like we would in biology divide
things into kingdoms and phyla and genus
and species and so on
what Montesquieu did was he said well
the basic patterns are these there are
all kinds of individual governments that
come and go throughout Western history
but there are three basic generic
forms of government that we find
historically there are are first of all
what you would call a dictatorship
and then there is second of all a
monarchy
or monarchial government
and third there is some form or another
of democratic government
now in analyzing these various forms of
government
historically
he looked for
laws
that apply
to government
just like Adam Smith In The Wealth of
Nations said there are laws that govern
economics
like the law of
of uh
scarcity and supply and demand gresham's
law that bad money drives out good money
and if you debase the currency the old
currency will suddenly pass out of
existence as it will be held by those
who are collecting it there's just as
today if you have silver coins from
before 1950 or so on their metal value
is higher than their
currency value so nobody will take a
silver 50 cent piece or a silver 25 cent
piece and go to the store and use it
interchangeably as a quarter because
it's silver content is so much higher
than the currency value the good money
has been driven out of circulation
that's one of the things that Adam Smith
noticed so what these people were doing
was that they were studying the
phenomena
that manifests itself in these fields
such as economics and and government and
so on
and looking for patterns looking for
Trends looking again for the logic of
the facts now when Montesquieu made his
application of government to history he
noticed that there were certain
basic underlying conditions that had to
be maintained for certain forms of
government to survive
and then he reduced these various
aspects to those things that he believed
were most necessary and I'll just give a
quick
example of this sort of thing he turns
his attention to these three forms of
government
and he said the single most important
necessary ingredient
for the successful continuity of a
dictatorship
is
fear
that dictators capitalize on fear in
order to stay in power
that's why when you find dictators
you'll find frequently secret police all
kinds of purges of
hostile opposition and so on
and people are oppressed under this kind
of a regime because when a dictator
rules there's always more power in the
masses than in the individual who holds
Sway and the only way he can keep
himself in power is to so intimidate the
masses and keep them afraid to revolt
and to rise up against his his
dictatorship that he has to have a reign
of terror in order to do that now we've
seen that over and over and over again
in history and certainly since the 18th
century with the uh the police state of
Russia and of Germany and other examples
of that around the world I remember when
LEC Valencia was placed under house
arrest
uh during the communist regime
I wondered what what was going to go on
there he had become so popular in Poland
and so famous that I figured that the
Soviets understood that if they killed
him
that it was actually too late to kill
him because he would become a martyr and
that could trigger a revolution because
what Valencia represented was one man
who stood against the system with
courage and that's the thing that will
always topple
dictatorships according to Montesquieu
now he also made this observation he
said that traditionally and historically
when one of these forms of government
Falls
it is inevitably or invariably replaced
by one of the other three
now coming down to monarchy he said that
the single most important ingredient for
a monarchy to survive is the principle
of Honor
that's why in the medieval times there
was so much attention given to Courtesy
which is a shortened word for two words
Court
etiquette
and you all have your your ladies and
Lords and the chivalry of all of that
business and the pageantry and the Pomp
and Circumstances that go with the with
the monarchy we see it today even in
England with all that goes on with the
royalty and all of the cursing and
bowing and and the uh the accoutrements
of a monarchical system the whole
principle here is that the royalty is to
be held in high esteem and in high honor
by the subjects to the king or to the
queen and then that works its way down
through the Dukes and the duchesses and
the Earls and the ladies and all of that
and whenever there is a loss of Honor
and the people no longer have respect
for their monarchical rulers than the
monarchy collapses now obviously we've
seen in in the Western World all kinds
of constitutional monarchies that don't
rule with the same kind of absolute
power that earlier forms of monarchy did
in Europe but we've seen for example the
crisis in England over the whole
business of the divorce pending divorce
between Charles and Diane
because all of a sudden the monarchy
even though it's only titular in its
representation was in serious trouble in
England because it had been disgraced
and once disgraced once the honor is
lost then with it comes the stability of
it
the third form of government is in its
broadly based format is the Democratic
form and the Democratic form
according which is I find interesting
according to Montesquieu finds as its
most important necessary condition
for its survival and for its continuity
of existence
is
what he called civic virtue
civic virtue
where there is an educated and
enlightened sense
of responsibility
and of obedience
civil obedience and of respect for law
and the idea is when the law is no
longer respected
and public morality fails
then inevitably the Democracy crumbles
and that's an interesting view because
now looking back to the beginnings of
this country which tried to follow uh
broadly a form of democratic government
even though it was constituted as a
republic nevertheless
we've seen that very crisis
attach itself to our own culture and
people wonder whether the grand
experience experiment of the American
model
is going to survive because of the loss
of civic virtue
and of course if it collapses then what
do you look for you look for either a
monarchy which is highly unlikely in
this day and age or
the worst alternative
the problem of dictatorship
well in any case these are the ways in
which the Enlightenment thinkers use the
new science to apply themselves to the
social sciences and one of the most
important social sciences that emerged
in the 18th century was that of
political Theory this is the Golden Age
of political Theory where all kinds of
new paradigms were emerging and new
thoughts were brought to the fore on how
to create an ideal form of government
and again that's tied into this business
of original sin
because in the past original sin meant
that people were corrupt and fallen and
could not govern themselves
but with the Triumph of the new humanism
and the rejection of this pessimistic
view of human nature came the view that
really what has to happen is the
Improvement of society and once
society's improved then human behavior
will improve and new forms of government
will be the key to bring in this kind of
utopian civilization well we'll see how
that works out in the broader
application of the theories of the
Enlightenment in our next session